Guide to the Springside Landscape Restoration Records, 1870-2024 (bulk 1972-2017)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
- Series IV. Site Plans and Maps, 1983-2000
  - Michael George and Lisa Dreishpoon-Weiss
    - "Plan of Master Plant Identification for Springside," preliminary analysis, 1987 Dec; [2 copies] (Folder 11.2 (Oversize))
  - Sandy and Babcock Association / The SWA Group
    - "A. J. Downing Original Site Plan,", 1987 (Folder 11.3 (Oversize))
    - "A. J. Downing - Springside,", 1987 (Folder 11.3 (Oversize))
    - "Revised Preliminary Site Plan,", 1984 Apr 17 (Folder 11.3 (Oversize))
    - "Site Analysis - Vegetation,", 1987 (Folder 11.3 (Oversize))
    - "Springside Existing Utilities & Topographic Data Map," sheet ST-1, 1985 Apr 23 (Folder 11.3 (Oversize))
  - Robert M. Toole
    - "Springside - Design Elements - 1852," Sheet A, revised, 1987 Apr 13 (Folder 11.4 (Oversize))
    - "Springside - Design Elements - 1852," Sheet A, annotated, 1990 Jul 10 (Folder 11.4 (Oversize))
    - "Springside - Existing Conditions - 1985," Sheet B, revised, 1986 Oct 25 (Folder 11.4 (Oversize))
    - "Springside - Existing Conditions - 1985," Sheet C, revised, 1986 Oct 25 (Folder 11.4 (Oversize))
  - Tourbier & Walmsley
    - "Existing Inventory of Major Trees,", 1999 Jun - 2000 Apr (Folder 11.4 (Oversize))
    - "Existing Inventory of Major Trees,", 1999 Jun - 2000 Apr (Box 12 (OV Roll))
  - Walmsley & Company, Inc. - "Master Plan for Restoring the Ornamental Farm of Matthew Vassar"
    - "1. Benson Lossing Site Description and Map, 1867,", 1988 (Box 12 (OV Roll))
    - "2a. Existing Conditions - Topography/Slopes,", 1988 (Box 13 (OV Roll))
    - "2b. Existing Conditions - Surface Water/Drainage,", 1988 (Box 13 (OV Roll))
    - "2c. Existing Conditions - Vegetation Types,", 1988 (Box 13 (OV Roll))
    - "2d. Existing Conditions - Circulation,", 1988 (Box 13 (OV Roll))
    - "2e. Existing Conditions - Buildings and Structures,", 1988 (Box 13 (OV Roll))
    - "3. Proposed Functional Subdivisions & Analysis,", 1988 (Folder 11.5 (Oversize))
    - "4. Master Plan,", 1988; [2 copies] (Folder 11.5 (Oversize))
    - "4. Springside Condominiums,", 1988 (Box 12 (OV Roll))
    - "4. Springside Condominiums," resized, colored, 1988 (Box 13 (OV Roll))
    - "5. Maintenance and Management Plan,", 1988; [2 copies] (Folder 11.5 (Oversize))
    - "5. Maintenance and Management Plan,", 1988 (Box 12 (OV Roll))
    - "5. Maintenance and Management Plan," resized, colored, 1988 (Box 13 (OV Roll))
    - "Existing Site Analysis,", 1988; [2 copies] (Folder 11.6 (Oversize))
    - "Historic Analysis,", 1988 (Folder 11.6 (Oversize))
    - "Management Analysis,", 1988 (Folder 11.6 (Oversize))
    - "Management Analysis,", 1988; [damaged] (Box 12 (OV Roll))
    - "Restoration Plan," drafts, 1988 Aug-Sep (Folder 11.6 (Oversize))
  - Miscellaneous
    - "Map of Springside (1857) by E. Jacob at Adriance," compact disc, undated; [1 CD] (Folder 6.31)
    - Springside, overhead photograph, undated (Box 12 (OV Roll))
    - Springside, partial site plan, undated (Box 12 (OV Roll))
    - "Subdivision of Lands, Springside Condominiums, Inc., 181 Academy St," perimeter survey, 1988 Nov 30 (Box 12 (OV Roll))
- Series V. Proposals, Reports, and Surveys, 1972-2023
  - Proposals
    - "A Master Plan for the Historic Landscape at 'Springside'" by Doell & Doell, 1987 Jul 16 (Folder 6.32)
    - "A Proposal for the Analysis, Preservation, & Management of Springside…" by LANDSCAPES with David Schuyler, Noel Dorsey Vernon, ASLA, Grossman & Associates, Inc., and William A. Patterson, 1987 Jul 13 (Folder 6.33)
    - "Proposal for Springside" by Walmsley & Company, Inc., 1987 Jul 10 (Folder 6.34)
    - "The Restoration of Springside" by Bruce Kelly and David Varnell (Landscape Architects), 1987 Jul 13 (Folder 6.35)
    - "Site Analysis Proposal for Springside" prepared by Rudy J. Favretti and Associates, 1987 Jul 9 (Folder 6.36)
    - "Springside Landscape Restoration: Historic Preservation Project,", 1987 Sep (Folder 6.37)
  - Reports
    - "Analysis of Effect of Proposed Project on 'Springside'" by City/Scape: Cultural Resource Consultants, 1999 Mar (Folder 6.38)
    - "Appraisal Report on Springside…" prepared by H. R. Fountain & Co., Inc., 1989-1990 (Folder 7.1)
    - "Archaeological Investigation, Springside," by STRATA Cultural Resource Management, LLC, 2013 Dec (Folder 7.2)
    - "Evaluation Report for Restoration Potential and Proposed Development at Springside" by Robert M. Toole, 1984 Feb 6 (Folder 7.3)
    - Historic American Building Survey, 1990 Apr (Folder 7.4)
    - "Historic Landscape Report for Springside" by Robert M. Toole, draft, 1985 May 15 (Folder 7.5)
    - "Historic Landscape Report for Springside" by Robert M. Toole, drafts and corrections, 1985-1986 (Folder 7.6)
    - "Historic Landscape Report for Springside" by Robert M. Toole, evaluations, 1986-1987 (Folder 7.7)
    - "Historic Landscape Report for Springside" by Robert M. Toole, draft, 1987 Jan 5 (Folder 7.8)
    - "Historic Landscape Report for Springside" by Robert M. Toole, final version, 1987 May 20 (Folder 7.9)
    - "Historic Landscape Report for Springside - Bibliography" by Robert M. Toole, 1986 Sep (Folder 7.10)
    - "Market Study of Springside Land Company, LCC" prepared by Pomeroy Appraisal Associates, 2010 Jan 7 (Folder 7.11)
    - National Register of Historic Landmarks, 1972 (Folder 7.12)
    - National Register of Historic Landmarks, 1982 (Folder 7.13)
    - "Phase 1B Archaeological Field Reconnaissance - Center Circle Carriageways, Springside…" prepared by Hartgen Archeological Associates, Inc., 2006 Apr (Folder 7.14)
    - "Preservation Maintenance Plan for a Historic Landscape: Springside" by Tourbier & Walmsley, 2000 May (Folder 7.15)
    - "Site Analysis of 'Springside" prepared by Walmsley & Company, Inc., 1988 Oct 19 (Folder 7.16)
    - "Site Analysis, Landscape Master Plan and Maintenance Plan of Springside National Historic Landmark" by Walmsley & Company, Inc., 1988 Dec 2 (Folder 7.17)
    - "Site Analysis, Landscape Master Plan and Maintenance Plan of Springside National Historic Landmark" by Walmsley & Company, Inc., circa 1989 (Folder 7.18)
    - "Site Analysis, Landscape Master Plan and Maintenance Plan of Springside National Historic Landmark" by Walmsley & Company, Inc., circa 1989 (Folders 7.19-7.20)
    - "Springside: A Partnership with the Environment" prepared by the Dutchess County Department of Planning, 1968 Dec (Folder 7.21)
    - "The Springside Cottage Outlook, Foundation Excavation, and Interpretation Recommendations" prepared by Kyle Toth, Marc Paalvast, and PS&S, 2023 May 12 (Folder 7.22)
    - Springside Drainage Study/ Sterling Properties proposed construction, 2004-2005 (Folder 7.23)
    - "Springside - Environmental Assessment Form,", 1983 Nov 10 (Folder 7.24)
    - "Springside - Environmental Assessment Form," supporting data and evaluation, 1983 Sep (Folder 7.25)
    - "Springside - Environmental Assessment Form," for Sterling Properties Group, revised, 2005 Mar 14 (Folders 7.26-7.27)
    - "Springside Porter's Cottage Exterior Paint Analysis" by Paul A. Baumgarten & Associates, 2005 (Folder 8.1)
    - "Working Paper #1 for Springside" by Walmsley & Company, Inc., 1988 Mar 14 (Folder 8.2)
  - Surveys - Vassar College Archaeological Field School
    - Proposal for research at Springside, 2001 (Folder 8.3)
    - Springside artifact catalog sheets, 2001 Sep-Nov (Folder 8.4)
    - Springside field notes, 2001 Sep-Nov (Folder 8.5)
    - Springside geophysical survey sheets, 2001 Sep-Nov (Folder 8.6)
    - Springside Archaeological Samples:
      - Barn Area - Test Pit, 2001 Sep-Nov (Box 10, Bag 1)
      - Between Jet Vale and Springside - Test Pit, Layer 1, Context 27, 2001 Sep-Nov (Box 10, Bag 2)
      - Between Jet Vale and Willow Spring - Layer 2, Context 28, 2001 Sep-Nov (Box 10, Bag 3)
      - Lawn Terrace - Grid 1, Unit 5, 2001 Sep-Nov (Box 10, Bag 4)
      - Lawn Terrace - Grid 2, Unit 1, Context 2, Level A, 2001 Nov 30 (Box 10, Bag 5)
      - Lawn Terrace - Grid 2, Unit 2, Context 8, 2001 Sep-Nov (Box 10, Bag 6)
      - Lawn Terrace - Grid 2, Unit 2, Context 16, 2001 Sep-Nov (Box 10, Bag 6)
      - Lawn Terrace - Grid 2, Unit 4, Context 1, Level A, 2001 Sep 28 (Box 10, Bag 7)
      - Lawn Terrace - Grid 2, Unit 4, Context 1, Level A, 2001 Sep-Nov (Box 10, Bag 8)
      - Lawn Terrace - Grid 3, Unit 9, Context 11, 2001 Sep-Nov (Box 10, Bag 9)
      - Lawn Terrace - Grid 3, Unit 9, Context 15, 2001 Sep-Nov (Box 10, Bag 10)
      - Lawn Terrace - Grid 3, Unit 10, Context 22C, 2001 Sep-Nov (Box 10, Bag 11)
      - Lawn Terrace - Grid 3, Unit 11, Context 18, 2001 Oct 12 (Box 10, Bag 12)
      - Lawn Terrace - Grid 3, Unit 12, 2001 Oct (Box 10, Bag 13)
      - Springside Cottage - Test Pit 1, 2001 Sep-Nov (Box 10, Bag 14)
      - Springside Cottage - Test Pit 2, 2001 Sep-Nov (Box 10, Bag 15)
- Series VI. Writings and Publications, 1950-2017
  - Bulletin of American Garden History, 1987 Spring (Folder 8.7)
  - Clark, Kitty, "Springside: An Exemplary American Home" (ART 250), 1987 Dec (Folder 8.8)
  - The Clearview Navigator, 1984-1985 (Folder 8.9)
  - Clippings, 1852-1900 (photocopies), undated (Folder 8.10)
  - Clippings, 1965-1979 (Folder 8.11)
  - Clippings, 1983-1988 (Folder 8.12)
  - Clippings, 1992-1998 (Folder 8.13)
  - Clippings, 2001-2006, 2017 (Folder 8.14)
  - Clippings: John O. Whitehouse, E. N. Howell, and William Nelson at Springside (photocopies), 1879-1973 (Folder 8.15)
  - Dutchess County Environmental Management Council, "The Lower Wappinger: A Significant Area,", 1982 Dec (Folder 8.16)
  - Effron, Jesse, "How Springside, An Important National Landmark, Was Saved," draft, 1988 Nov (Folder 8.17)
  - Flad, Harvey, "Matthew Vassar's 'Springside'," correspondence, 1986-1990 (Folder 8.18)
  - Flad, Harvey, "Matthew Vassar's 'Springside'," drafts, circa 1987 (Folder 8.19)
  - Flad, Harvey, "Matthew Vassar's 'Springside'," drafts, 1987 Aug - 1988 Jan (Folder 8.20)
  - Flad, Harvey, "Matthew Vassar's 'Springside'," final draft, circa 1988 (Folder 8.21)
  - Flad, Harvey, "Matthew Vassar's 'Springside'," drafts for Dumbarton Oaks Colloquium, circa 1987 (Folder 8.22)
  - Flad, Harvey, "Matthew Vassar's 'Springside'," research and notes, 1986-1987 (Folder 8.23)
  - Flad, Harvey, "Matthew Vassar's 'Springside' As Designed by Downing and Vaux,", undated (Folder 8.24)
  - Flad, Harvey, "Meaning (and Mortality) In Preserved Landscapes,", undated (Folder 8.25)
  - Flad, Harvey - Mohonk Garden Conference, notes and research, 1988 (Folder 8.26)
  - Flad, Harvey, "Past, Present, and Future Imperfect: The Practice of Historic Landscape Preservation at Andrew Jackson Downing's Springside,", 1996 (Folder 8.27)
  - Flad, Harvey - Research and notes, Andrew Jackson Downing, 1985-2000 (Folder 8.28)
  - Flad, Harvey - Research, Andrew Jackson Downing letters from Sleepy Hollow Restorations (photocopies), 1987 May (Folder 8.29)
  - Flad, Harvey, "Saving Springside: Preserving Downing's Last Landscape," drafts, 2017 (Folder 8.30)
  - Flad, Harvey, "Saving Springside: Preserving Downing's Last Landscape," final draft, with correspondence, 2017 Jul (Folder 8.31)
  - The Garden Conservancy Newsletter, 1996-2005 (Folder 8.32)
  - "History of Springside,", undated (Folder 8.33)
  - Hudson River Quarterly, 1979 Winter (Folder 8.34)
  - Hudson River Valley Greenway, "Hudson River Valley National Heritage Area Management Plan,", 2002 Jun (Folder 8.35)
  - Hudson Valley Philharmonic, "Designer's Showhouse '83,", 1983 (Folder 8.36)
  - Miscellaneous writings about Springside, undated (Folder 8.37)
  - New York State Bureau of Historic Sites, "Historic Preservation Manual,", 1984 Nov (Folder 8.38)
  - Pendleton, Christopher, "A Preliminary Geologic Study of Springside Estate National Historic Landmark" (Vassar College senior thesis), 1992 May 5 (Folder 8.39)
  - "Prophet With Honor: The Career of Andrew Jackson Downing, 1815-1852," Dumbarton Oaks Colloquium on the History of Landscape Architecture XI, 1989 (Folder 8.40)
  - Research - Andrew Jackson Downing Memorial Park, Newburgh, NY, 1990-1991 (Folder 9.1)
  - Research - Springside, undated (Folder 9.2)
  - Research - Stonework, 2004-2007 (Folder 9.3)
  - Sears, John F., "Andrew Jackson Downing and Picturesque Tourism at Matthew Vassar's 'Springside',", 1990 (Folder 9.4)
  - Small, Virginia, "Learning from Legendary Garden Designers," Fine Gardening, 2001 Jan-Feb (Folder 9.5)
  - "Springside History,", 1950-1988 (Folder 9.6)
  - "Springside History,", 1990-2004 (Folder 9.7)
  - Springside Landscape Restoration Newsletter, 1994 Dec (Folder 9.8)
  - Springside Landscape Restoration Newsletter, 1997-2000 (Folder 9.9)
  - Springside Landscape Restoration Newsletter, 2001-2005 (Folder 9.10)
  - "Springside Mazurka," sheet music with notes, 1992 (Folder 9.11)
  - Toole, Robert M., "1820-1880, Romantic Gardens on the Hudson River, New York State,", 1984 (Folder 9.12)
  - Toole, Robert M., "Springside: Andrew Jackson Downing's Only Extant Garden,", 1987 Sep 20 (Folder 9.13)
  - Wahlberg, Holly, "Statement of Significance: Springside Landscape,", 2017 (Folder 9.14)
  - Writings on Andrew Jackson Downing and landscaping, 1986-2005 (Folder 9.15)
- Series VII. Nelson Family Papers, 1870-2024
  - Advertisement for sale of Springside by auctioneer Adrian H. Miller & Son, 1879 Jun (Folder 11.7 (Oversize))
  - Letters about Springside, 1879 - circa 1970 (photocopies), undated (Folder 9.16)
  - Notes on Springside by Miles Nelson, 2023-2024 (Folder 9.17)
  - Photographs - Springside property and Nelson family, circa 1897-1959 (Folder 9.18)
  - Site plan - "Marie Nelson Estate - Right of Way,", 1954 Jul 15 (Folder 11.7 (Oversize))
  - Site plan - "Springside,", 1931 Mar (Folder 11.7 (Oversize))
  - Site plan - "Springside,", 1959 Oct 14 (Folder 11.7 (Oversize))
  - Site plan - "Springside," annotated, 1959 Oct 14 (Folder 11.7 (Oversize))
  - Site plan - "Springside - Marie Nelson Estate and Surrounding Properties,", circa 1965 (Folder 11.7 (Oversize))
  - Springside - Deed, 1879 Jun 26 (Folder 9.19)
  - Springside - Referee's Deed, 1870 Jul 9 (Folder 9.20)
  - Springside - Referee's Deed, mortgage foreclosure, 1901 Apr 29 (Folder 9.21)
  - Springside - "Search against the premises in the Town of Poughkeepsie described in a deed made by John P. H. Tallman…,", 1879 Jul 11 (Folder 9.22)
  - Springside - Terms of Sale, 1879 Mar 5 (Folder 9.23)